[Music]
as I explained in my last video when our
blood volume drops our kidneys detected
and angot tensin is released when our
blood volume Rises on the other hand our
heart detects it and releases a hormone
called A&P atrial natriuretic peptide
also known as ANF atrial nature uretic
Factor we used to think our heart was
just a pump but now we know it's also a
gland there are stretch receptors in the
first chamber of our heart and when
extra blood pours Into the Heart A&P is
released what does it do as the title of
review in a obesity Journal put it heart
hormones fuel a fire in fat if you drip
amp on human fat and muscle tissue fat
is rapidly released and the muscle cells
ramp up their capacity to burn it Infuse
amp into people and the rate at which
fat is mobilized and burned can shoot up
15% you can take muscle biopsies from
people and show how much better their
muscles get at burning fat in the
presence of elevated amp levels no
surprise then that obese and overweight
individuals tend to have considerably
lower levels in their bloodstream so the
weight to a person's stomach may be
through their
heart why would this stretch sensitive
heart hormone tap into our fat stores
well when does the heart get stretched
during intense physical activity uh we
used to think it was just the adrenaline
type hormones that are released when you
exercise that mobilize fat from our
tissues but now we know that& from our
heart plays a key role as well inject
people with the amount of& you they
normally get in their system when
exercising and their whole body fat
burning goes up even if they're just
sitting on the couch how else can we
stretch our heart that extra little bit
to release amp by increasing our blood
volume by drinking extra water when you
don't drink for 12 hours straight your a
levels in your blood Fall by about 25%
but chug down about four glasses of
water in your levels can jump up by 50%
within 90 minutes now that's too much to
drink at one time but it can't offer a
sense of how much potential control we
have over this fat burning
hormone how else could we trick our body
into producing this exercise hormone
without lacing up our gym shoes
if it's all about pulling extra blood
into our heart what about lying with our
head tilted down sounds kind of funny
but researchers took the possibility
seriously enough to run the experiment
they laid people down at just a 6° angle
a slight tilt this like putting three or
four bricks under the posts at the foot
of your bed so it's not like you're
hanging upside down uh they were almost
flat but at just enough of a slant for
Gravity to draw extra blood into their
to torso within an hour their amp levels
doubled and stayed up for the 4 hours
the experiment
ran okay but did they all of a sudden
start burning more fat yes the
proportion of fat they were burning is
fuel shut up by 40% and they were just
lying down the whole time so what if you
tried sleeping with a slight head down
tilt by putting a few bricks under the
post at the foot of your bed would it
cause you to burn more fat while you
slept all I'll address the potential
pros and
cons next
[Music]